Guide to the Thomas Wentworth Higginson Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Wentworth Higginson collection, 1852-1907.
YCAL MSS 549
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection contains correspondence and writings of Thomas Wentworth Higginson. Correspondence consists of autograph letters, signed to various individuals. Writings consist of manuscript writings drafts and notes.
Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. Provenance information was transcribed from catalog cards and is listed at the folder level. Unless otherwise noted, material was a gift of Owen F. Aldis, 1911.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911)
Thomas Wentworth Higginson, American Unitarian minister, author, abolitionist, and soldier.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence and writings of Thomas Wentworth Higginson. Correspondence consists of autograph letters, signed to various individuals. Writings consist of manuscript writings drafts and notes.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1852-1907. II. Writings, 1864-1906.
American literature -- 19th century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors -- United States -- 19th century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911
- Correspondence, 1852-1907; Series I; 53
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Aldis, "Judge", 1878-1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alger, Abby, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barstow, Eliza Willis, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Best, "Mr.", 1896 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Booth, "Miss", 1884 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Botta, Mrs. Vincenzo, 1876 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Buck, Mrs., 1877 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Custodial History
    Gift of Reverend K. W. Cameron, 1961
  - Coe, "Miss", 1894 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Gift of James T. Babb, 1959
  - Drake, "Mr.", 1887 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dwight, "Mr.", 1884 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Eliot, Samuel, 1871 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fields, Osgood & C., 1869 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Foley, P. K., 1905, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Goss, F. M., 1884 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hames, E. H. & Co., 1879 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Harris, T. W., 1878 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Howland, "Mrs.", 1871 October 12 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Larcom, Lucy, 1889 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lee & Shepard, 1874 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Livermore, "Mr.", 1894 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Gift of C. B. Tinker, 1934
  - "Mead", 1907 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miller, "Mr.", 1885 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Niles, J., Jr., 1890 December 4 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Norton, Charles Eliot, 1887 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Parsons, "Professor", 1872 August 17 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Gift of C. B. Tinker, 1939
  - Parsons, "Miss", 1886, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Gift of James T. Babb, 1959 and Sidney W. Davidson, 1957
  - Peabody, "Dr.", 1886 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pierce, John, 1885 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Poole, "Mr.", 1884 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Porter, "Miss", 1889 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Rideing, "Mr.", 1887 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Gift of James T. Babb
  - Roberts Brothers, 1890 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Gift of William H. McCarthy, Jr., 1932
  - Stoddard, Charles Warren, 1869 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Taylor, Mr., 1898, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Thompson, Edwin, 1852 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ward, "Mrs.", 1897 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Willis, George, 1852 February 29 (Box 1, Folder 36a)
  - Wilson, "Gen.", 1886 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Young, "Mr.", undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Purchased on the Alvord Fund.
  - To "booksellers", 1880 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Miss Ellen", 1876 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "Dear Professor", undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Purchased on the Alvord Fund, 1959
  - "Dear Sir", 1856 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "Dear Sir", 1859 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "Dear Sir", 1860 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Dear Sir, 1865 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "Dear Sir", 1866 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "Dear Sir", 1881 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "Dear Sir", 1887 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "Dear Sir", undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Unidentified, 1861 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Unidentified, 1875 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Unidentified, 1887 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Writings, 1864-1906; Series II; 10
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  All writings are autograph manuscript drafts.
  - "Boston", 1893 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "Childhood's Fancies", undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "Decoration", 1873 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld, 1961
  - "Forward: from the German of Hoffman von Fallersleben", undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Introduction to The Book of Elizabethan Verse, circa 1906 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Quotation of a paragraph from The Procession of the Flowers, 1871 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - "The Romance of a Poor Young Man", 1878 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - "Ultra-Marine", 1875 August (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Purchased from Morton on the Alvord and GBF funds, 1960
  - Autograph quotation signed, 1865 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Gift of James T. Babb, 1962
  - Autograph note signed concerning James Russell Lowell's Fireside Travels, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 62)